## Kathleen T Quach

San Diego, CA

## Summary.

A **behavioral neuroscientist** with ten years of independent research experience, specializing in the application of ethological, neuroeconomic, and other behavioral frameworks to analyze decision-making processes of both predator and prey in naturalistic predator-prey interactions in a laboratory setting.

## **Education**

#### University of California, San Diego (UCSD)

La Jolla, CA, USA

PhD in Neurosciences, Specialization in Computational Neuroscience

2019

• GPA: 3.734 / 4.000

### University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

BS in Neuroscience

2010

• GPA: 3.618 / 4.000

## Research Experience\_

#### Salk Institute for Biological Studies (Molecular Neurobiology, PI: Sreekanth Chalasani)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Postdoctoral Fellow

2019.09 - 2024.04

- Led projects investigating the decision-making and molecular regulation of defensive behaviors by *Caenorhabditis elegans* nematodes in response to *Pristionchus pacificus* predators.
- Integrated concepts from predatory imminence theory and prey refuge theory to build a behavioral framework that can be used to predict, elicit, and interpret *Caenorhabditis elegans* defensive behaviors in response to changes in various dimensions of perceived predation risk.
- Conducted behavioral experiments on genetic mutants and transgenic strains to identify changes in interdependence between signaling partners across stages of defensive behaviors.

#### Salk Institute for Biological Studies (Molecular Neurobiology, PI: Sreekanth Chalasani)

La Jolla, CA, USA

**Graduate Student** 

2012.07 - 2019.09

- Led projects investigating the decision-making and molecular regulation of foraging decisions by *Pristionchus pacificus* predatory nematodes in response to predator-prey competition with *Caenorhabditis elegans* prey nematodes.
- Integrated concepts from foraging theory, neuroeconomic theory, and intraguild predation theory to build a behavioral framework that can be used to predict, elicit, and distinguish between predatory and territorial motivations for attacking *Caenorhabditis elegans*.
- Conducted a screen of pharmacologically active compounds to identify signaling mechanisms underlying the switch between predatory and territorial motivation, using the behavioral framework to directly target decision-making processes rather than motor or sensory processes.
- Other projects: Co-led a project investigating whole-brain activity of *Caenorhabditis elegans* nematodes to understand how state-dependent network interactions gate sensory input at the motor and command neuron level. Supported a project investigating neural regulation of hypoxia reponses in *Danio rerio* zebrafish.

### UCLA (Psychiatry and Biobehavioral Sciences, PI: Mirella Dapretto)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2009.02 - 2010.06

- Conducted independent research investigating abnormal effective connectivity during emotional face processing in children with autism spectrum disorder.
- Applied dynamic causal modeling to fMRI time series data to estimate directionality and strength of coupling between brain regions during viewing
  of emotional faces.
- Developed methods for automating data entry of survey inputs from test subjects.

#### UCLA (Neurology, PI: Jack Van Horn)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2010.01 - 2010.06

• Designed graphical user interface elements for Invizian neuroinformatics software.

## UCLA (Psychiatry and Biobehavioral Sciences, PI: Susan Bookheimer)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2009.03 - 2010.06

- Scored eye gaze behavior of 36-month old infants with autism spectrum disorder and their siblings during social interaction with caregivers and strangers.
- Drew regions of interests to quantify how much time is spent looking at facial, body, and background features.
- Developed code for automated parsing of Tobii software output.

MAY 1, 2024

Undergraduate Research and Therapist Assistant

2007.06 - 2009.09

- · Assisted in cognitive behavioral therapy for treatment of anxiety in children with autism spectrum disorder.
- · Performed data entry of therapy intake assessments and patient questionnaires for analysis in SPSS.

## **Industry Experience**

#### **Starbucks Coffee Company**

Seattle, WA, USA

Implementation Specialist

2011.12 - 2012.06

 Analyzed data and implemented strategies for optimizing the function of retail networks and public Wi-Fi in over 10,000 Starbucks stores across North America.

## **Teaching and Outreach Experience**

#### Salk Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF)

La Jolla, CA, USA

**Application Reviewer** 

2023.11 - 2023.12

• Reviewed anonymized applications based on a rubric that assessed need and career goals.

#### Salk Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Developer & Presenter

2023.06.12

• Developed and presented a workshop (*Thinking like a Scientist*), introducing undergraduate interns to the values and philosophy guiding scientific research, and the principles of fostering a scientific personality resilient to failures and biases.

#### Salk Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Mentor

2022.05 - 2022.08, 2023.05 - 2023.08

· Intensively mentored undergraduates from under-resourced institutions to perform independent research in a 10-week program.

### **UCSD Biology Undergraduate and Master's Mentorship Program (BUUMP)**

La Jolla, CA, USA

Mentor

2020.09 - 2021.02

• Mentored biology undergraduate students from underrepresented minorities.

## UCSD Graduate Division (Course: Fundamentals of Statistics and Computation for Neuroscientists)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Course Developer & Instructor

2016.03 - 2016.06

Developed and taught a graduate-level introductory course designed to provide literacy in and exposure to computational techniques.

# UCSD Graduate Division (Course: Introduction to Methods in Computational Neuroscience, Instructor: Pam Reinegal)

La Jolla. CA. USA

Teaching Assistant

2015.09 - 2015.12

Assisted in teaching a graduate-level course on mathematical foundations and applications of computational neuroscience methods.

Monarch School San Diego, CA, USA

Tutor

2022.09 - 2022.11

· Tutored chemistry to students impacted by homelessness to compensate for shortage of science teachers.

## **Publications**

**Quach, K. T.\***, Hughes, G. A., & Chalasani, S. H. (2024). Interdependence between SEB-3 and NLP-49 peptides shifts across predator-induced defensive behavioral modes in *Caenorhabditis elegans*. Submitted to *eLife*.

**Quach, K. T.**, & Chalasani, S. H. (2022). Flexible reprogramming of *Pristionchus pacificus* motivation for attacking *Caenorhabditis elegans* in predator-prey competition. *Current Biology*, 32(8), 1675-1688.

Cecere, Z. T.\*, Quach, K. T.\*, Yemini, E., How, J. J., Sharpee, T. O., & Chalasani, S. H. (2021). State-dependent network interactions differentially gate sensory input at the motor and command neuron level in *Caenorhabditis elegans*. bioRxiv, 2021-04. \*co-first authors

**Quach, K. T.**, & Chalasani, S. H. (2020). Intraguild predation between *Pristionchus pacificus* and *Caenorhabditis elegans*: a complex interaction with the potential for aggressive behaviour. *Journal of neurogenetics*, 34(3-4), 404-419.

Abstracts and .pdf versions are available at kathleenqua.ch/publications.

May 1, 2024

## **Awards**

2022.12 - 2024.11	Maximillian E. and Marion O. Hoffman Foundation Award
2020.06 - 2022.06	Paul F. Glenn Center for Biology of Aging Research Fellow
2018.07 - 2019.07	Salk Women and Science Award
2018.03 - 2019.03	Mary K. Chapman Foundation Award
2018.10 - 2018.03	Jesse and Caryl Philips Foundation Award
2016.05.21	UCSD Neurosciences Graduate Teaching Award
2014.09 - 2017.08	National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellow

## **Laboratory Skills**

Model Organisms Caenorhabditis elegans (nematode), Pristionchus pacificus (nematode), Danio rerio (zebrafish), human

**Behavior** predator-prey interaction, foraging, chemotaxis, adaptation, exploration, egg-laying

**Microscopy** brightfield/DIC/fluorescence, light/confocal, laser microsurgery, calcium imaging, expansion

**Staining** immunocytochemistry, Dil/DiO (neuronal tracer), Oil Red O (fat)

**Pharmacology** drug screens using LOPAC 1280, neurotransmitters and associated agonists/antagonists, paralytics

**Bacteria** culturing/incubation, streaking/spreading/plating, colony counting, spectrophotometry, transformation, antibiotic selection

**Microfluidics** device fabrication, device operation, automated control of laminar flows

**Molecular biology** cloning, DNA/RNA purification, PCR, primer design, gel electrophoresis, DNA/RNAseq, DNA/RNA quantity/quality assessment

## Computational Methods \_\_\_\_\_

**Theories & Frameworks** foraging theory, expected utility theory, intraguild predation theory, predatory imminence theory, prey refuge theory,

information theory

Statistics tests for nominal variables, parametric/non-parametric tests for one/multiple measurement variable(s), ANCOVA,

linear/nonlinear correlation, linear/logistic regression models, linear mixed-effects models, bootstrapping, data

transformation, distributional analysis, power analysis, machine-learning

**Image Processing** image segmentation, image deconvolution, morphological processing, fluorescence intensity quantification, color

deconvolution

**Neural Dynamics** time series analysis, dimensionality reduction, network analysis, network modeling

## Software, Platforms, & Languages \_\_\_\_\_

Scientific Computing MATLAB, R

**Image Acquisition and Processing** ImageJ, Zen, Streampix, Metamorph

**Bioinformatics** APE, Geneious, BLAST, Primer-BLAST, Galaxy, UCSD Genome Browser, IGV

**OS** Windows, Linux (Ubuntu)

**Adobe** Acrobat, Illustrator, Photoshop, InDesign

Microsoft Office Word, Excel, OneNote

**Google** Drive, Docs, Sheets, Slides, Forms

**Collaboration** Zoom, Slack

**Electronic Lab Notebook** Benchling

**Command Line** BASH, Powershell

**Web** HTML, Markdown, CSS

**Typesetting** LTFX, Overleaf, TeXmaker

Version Control Git, Github
Container Docker

**IDE** Visual Studio

**Data Serialization Formats** JSON, YAML

**Diagramming** PlantUML

May 1, 2024